# Nicholas Spyrison, Ph.D.

Machine Learning | Dimension Reduction

Parker, CO 80134

② (720) 765-1836

☑ spyrison@gmail.com

☐ nspyrison.netlify.com/
③ github.com/nspyrison

In linkedin.com/in/nspyrison/

# Career Summary

A published data scientist with years of experience hypothesis testing, experimental design, enterprise-level reporting, and machine learning on a diverse range of data. Conducted end-to-end development on multiple R packages delivering open-source solutions to the community. Nick frequently acts as a mentor to sharing best practices with the team resulting in continuous improvement, performance code, and increase project completion.

# Employment History

06/2022 – 01/2023 Research Data Scientist, University of Queensland,

Clayton, VIC.

- Lead end-to-end analysis of the largest global COVID-19 patient-level data resulting in several submitted journal articles on kidney health outcomes
- Delivered batteries of models varying cohorts, model formulas, and hyperparameters tuning on patient-level health data

07/2018 – 10/2022 **Research Officer**, *Monash University*,

Clayton, VIC.

- Data Fluency Instructor: Lead workshops (10-30 people) on statistical modeling, R, Python, PowerBI, and Git
- Teaching Assistant: Post-grad tutorials on high-dimensional data analysis, post-grad data visualization, business and undergrad economic statistics
- o Research Officer: Extract, transform, load, and analysis of census and text data

12/2016 – 1/2018 Business Intelligence Developer, CPI Card Group,

Denver, CO.

- SQL reporting; across 4 reporting platforms and 4 severs
- Mentor junior teammates and improve query performance
- Triage and transfer 30+ legacy reports to modern reporting solution
- Developed supply chain report tracking a cost reduction of more than \$4M USD

 $07/2015-10/2016 \quad \textbf{Business Intelligence Developer}, \ \textit{UDR Real Estate Investment Trust},$ 

Denver, CO.

 $\circ\,$  Transition enterprise footprint from WebFOCUS to SSRS – 10+ reports

11/2014 - 04/2015 Business Intelligence Analyst, Heartland Financial USA,

Dubuque, IA.

o Financial reporting for internal and external audiences

02/2013 - 05/2014 **Delivery Analyst**, *IBM - International Business Machines*,

Dubuque, IA.

- Automated ETL with VBA macros for about 0.5 FTE savings across the team
- KPI reporting to teams and management

01/2010 - 08/2012 Laboratory Technician, The Ames Laboratory & Iowa State University,

Ames, IA.

# Authored Software (R Packages)

09/2022 **cheem** – Novel analysis and interactive visual for exploring ML interpretability  $\underline{\textit{Link}}$ 

10/2020 **spinifex** – ggplot2-like API for composing and exporting animated projections

<u>Link</u>

### Education

02/2018 - 06/2022 Ph.D. Information Technology & Statistics, Monash University, Clayton, VIC, Dimension reduction, interactive and animated data visualization, machine learning

Thesis: Interactive and Dynamic Visualization of High-dimensional Data.

- Novel interoperability visualization methods for Fit random forest models on several contemporary datasets also shown to generalize to other models with SVM and XGboost
- o Utilized SHAP and LIME local explanations to explore local linear variable importance to understand large residuals in the models
- Created **novel interactive animation** facilitating this exploration in a web app
- Authored an R packages on CRAN as free and open source work in improve reproducibility and contribute back to the community

08/2008 - 05/2012 B.Sc. Statistics, Iowa State University, minors in Physics and Mathematics, Ames, IA.

#### Technical Skills

Programs R, SQL, Python, Git, GitHub, LaTeX, Excel, VBA

Packages ggplot2, tidyverse, plotly, shiny, tidymodels, caret, keras, pandas, scikit-learn

Reporting SSRS, Tableau, PowerBI, Rmarkdown, Shiny

#### Awards and Honors

06/2022	Invited article for INFORM's OR/MS Tomorrow	<u>Link</u>
04/2022	RStudio: March "Top 40" New CRAN Packages	<u>Link</u>
05/2022	Monash Postgraduate Publication Award	
10/2020	Melbourne Datathon 2020 – 1st place of several hundred entries	<u>Link</u>
	o Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions	S
11/2018	ACEMS Impact and Engagement Award	
07/2018	UseR2018 Datathon – 3rd place	
	<ul> <li>Spatio temporal animated visualization of over 7 million avian sightings</li> </ul>	
2018 – 2022	Faculty Graduate Research Scholarship	
2018 – 2022	Co-funded Monash Graduate Scholarship	
05/2012	Nominated for Student Employee of the Year	
05/2011	Nominated for Student Employee of the Year	

## **Publications**

05/2008 American Legion Award

#### **Doctoral Thesis**

Nicholas S Spyrison. "Interactive and dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. PhD thesis. [1] Monash University, Mar. 2022. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/thesis\_ns/blob/master/ docs/thesis\_ns.pdf.

#### Journal Articles

- Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. "spinifex: an R Package for Creating a Manual Tour of Lowdimensional Projections of Multivariate Data". en. In: The R Journal 12.1 (2020), p. 243. ISSN: 2073-4859. DOI: 10.32614/RJ-2020-027. URL: https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2020/RJ-2020-027/index.html (visited on 10/16/2020).
- [3] Stuart Lee et al. "The state-of-the-art on tours for dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. In: WIREs Computational Statistics (Dec. 2021), p. 21. ISSN: 1939-0068. DOI: 10.1002/wics.1573. URL: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/wics.1573 (visited on 12/10/2021).

- [4] Nicholas Spyrison, Dianne Cook, and Przemyslaw Biecek. "Exploring Local Explanations of Nonlinear Models Using Animated Linear Projections". In: arXiv preprint, submitted to JMLR (2022). DOI: 10. 48550/ARXIV.2205.05359. URL: https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.05359.
- [5] Nicholas Spyrison, Dianne Cook, and Kim Marriott. "A Study on a User-Controlled Radial Tour for Variable Importance in High-Dimensional Data". In: arXiv preprint, submitted to TVCG (Dec. 2022). arXiv:2301.00077 [stat]. DOI: 10.48550/arXiv.2301.00077. URL: http://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00077 (visited on 01/06/2023).

#### Software (R Packages)

- [6] Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. *spinifex: Manual Tours, Manual Control of Dynamic Projections of Numeric Multivariate Data.* 2021. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=spinifex.
- [7] Nicholas Spyrison. cheem: Interactively Explore the Support of Local Explanations of a Model. 2022. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=cheem.

#### Conference Proceedings

- [8] Nicholas S. Spyrison. "spinifex: visualizing local structure of higher dimensions". en. In: Brisbane, Australia, 2018. URL: https://user2018.r-project.org/poster/ (visited on 07/28/2020).
- [9] Madeleine Barrow, Jieyang Chong, and Nicholas Spyrison. "Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions". en. In: *Melbourne Datathon 2020, Insights category*. Oct. 2020, p. 4. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/melb\_datathon2020/blob/master/\_paper/paper.pdf (visited on 02/09/2022).
- [10] Nicholas Spyrison, Benjamin Lee, and Lonni Besançon. ""Is IEEE VIS \*that\* good?" On key factors in the initial assessment of manuscript and venue quality". In: *IEEE AltVis Workshop*. type: article. July 2021. DOI: 10.31219/osf.io/65wm7. URL: https://osf.io/65wm7/ (visited on 08/21/2021).
- [11] Nicholas Spyrison. "Animated Linear Projections". In: Summer 2022. INFORMS, May 2022.

References and publications available on request.